so today we're going to learn about the
complete benefits of using quasi random
numbers and sequences in your monte
carlo simulation to get the best
accuracy with the lowest number of
random variables we're going to talk
about the disadvantages of using
pseudo-random numbers compared to
quasi-random numbers and then the
benefits that you can get in your monte
carlo simulation to date we've been
looking at variance reduction techniques
where the whole aim has been we want to
decrease the amount of random numbers
that we have to compute in order to get
the most accurate option valuation
possible and we're going to see just how
much of a big difference it makes using
quasi random numbers so let's get into
it first we're going to talk about
generating random numbers for monte
carlo so to simulate our wrist neutral
price paths in derivative evaluation
through monte carlo simulation we lean
heavily on brownian motions and this is
the generation of standard normal random
variables within our simulation now it's
important to note most programming
languages and spreadsheets like excel
include a uniform pseudo random number
generator this is going to generate
integers between 0 and a specified upper
value where each integer occurs with
equal probability so a standard uniform
random generator follows the
mathematical definition of real values
in the range between 0 and 1 where again
all these real values in that range are
equally likely so a pseudo random number
generator is an algorithm for generating
a sequence of numbers whose properties
approximate the properties of sequences
of random numbers they're not actually
random the generated sequence is not
truly random because it is completely
determined on an initial value which is
called the seed
they are important for reproducibility
in the case of monte carlo simulation
and other simulation methods and also
the speed of generation so with a
standard uniform random number generator
we can convert these to standard normal
random numbers how do we do that so
let's first import our dependencies
we've got time numpy scipy stats module
and then we're importing matplotlib pi
plot so let's investigate the first
method for creating the standard normal
random variables from our uniform
distribution
so we're going to approximate it with 12
uniform samples so what we're going to
do a common approach is actually to
generate 12 standard normal random
numbers add them together and subtract 6
from the total the distribution of this
combination has a 0 mean and a variance
of one which is exactly what we need for
the normal distribution
so we're going to make our random c
equal to one and then we're going to
have uh base e to the power of six
number of random variables i've created
a function here which is add 12 uniform
so what we're going to do is we're going
to sample 12 variables from our uniform
distribution between 0 and 1 and then
we're going to sum them up and then -6
and we're going to do this for a large
number of n so we're going to time this
and see how long it takes so the
computation was about 3.3 seconds so
remember that so now we're going to look
at some of the statistics so we have the
mean standard deviation skew and
kurtosis and remember the standard
deviation is going to equal the variance
when the standard deviation is 1. so
we've got a variance of 1 and a mean of
0. so it's been a good approximation for
the normal distribution but where it
falls short is that we have a kotosis
now the way the kurtosis is calculated
in numpy is that they've subtracted
three so obviously normal distribution
has a ketosis of three whereas this has
a little bit less than a ketosis of
three so with that in mind what we
notice is that it's a good approximation
however we we understand that the
maximum values are minus six and six
with this methodology whereas there is a
very small percentage chance that in the
normal distribution we can actually
calculate and have uh random normal
values that are that are higher or lower
than that and then we also notice that
the ketosis is a little less than three
which means that too many values will be
generated closer to the mean so let's
look at a better solution which is the
box mueller transformation so this is an
alternative method where we actually
select exact transformation of pairs of
standard uniform random numbers to pairs
of standard normal random numbers so
we're going to say that we have two
standard uniformly distributed random
pairs x1 and x2 and then we're going to
create standard normally distributed
pairs z1 and z2 and they can be obtained
with a following transformation
so i've coded that up here in our box
mueller
function here and then we've added these
together it's important to know here
with a box miller method that we're
actually having to generate two random
normal distributed variables at once so
what i've done is i've taken that in and
i've divided it by two we can see here
that we've had an incredible decrease in
the computation time from 3 seconds down
to 0.05 now so much more efficient
method of actually calculating
random normal variables so let's take a
look at our distribution again we have a
mean that's extremely close to 0 and
then we've got a standard deviation of
one a variance of one and we've got a
kurtosis which is much closer to three
and in this case zero because numpy
minus is three
now we're going to look at method number
three the masala polar rejection so
this also requires pairs of uniformly
distributed random numbers and to avoid
using the trigonometric functions of the
box muller transformations let's
consider polar coordinates so for this
we're going to consider random variables
x 1 and x 2 uniformly distributed now
not from 0 to 1 but -1 to 1 interval
that's important such that
this can be generated as follows and
you've got a picture of the unit circle
here so
we've got x1 squared plus x2 squared is
less than one so it's everything that
falls within the boundaries of the unit
circle
coordinates so picture the unit circle
and we have at the center of it our
coordinate zero zero what we're doing
here is essentially we're getting uh
from pythagoras theorem we're getting
that length that c value um and then we
that's w essentially it's c squared so
it's the length squared of the unit
circle and what we're saying is we want
it to be within the circle so while w is
greater than or equal to 1 i want to
keep on sampling standard uniform random
numbers until this satisfy satisfies
this constraint when it's less than one
when it's within the unit circle then i
want to calculate my c parameter which
is the square root of minus two log w
over w and then we can calculate our
random normally distributed pairs
so i've coded that up in our polar
rejection function here and we've got
this while loop so while any and i'm
using numpy arrays here so we've got
this sum of squared function which is
able to calculate the w and then we're
looking for the condition where the sum
of the squares of our uniform
distributed numbers our pairs of
variables is greater than or equal to 1.
and while we still have that true then i
want to keep sampling and replacing
those pairs so really this is supposed
to be a more efficient method for
actually
calculating random normal distributions
but because of some of the arrays that
i'm using here in numpy arrays it's been
a little bit slower at .117 but still
very much better than simulating 12
variables
so let's look at some properties again
we have a very low kurtosis and we've
got the mean and standard deviation of
one so we're getting a more accurate
representation with our polarity
rejection method
now the last method that i want to talk
about here and this is really what
numpy is using in the background is
we've got an inverse transform sampling
so all we're saying is we want to use
the uniform
distribution as an input to be able to
generate our random normally distributed
variables using this inverse cdf
function so now the cumulative density
function of a standard normal
distribution is given like this and
we're all very familiar with this but
this leads to a problem because it can
be shown that the integral of e to the
power negative x squared
has no closed form so using the standard
elementary functions and that means we
have no way of finding a closed form for
the normal cdf
it's important to note that this is a
difficult distribution to work with
because there are closed form inverse
cdfs for the exponential the pariato the
cauchy the logistic the rayleigh
distributions you name it but
unfortunately for the normal
distribution we can't now thankfully we
have a work around and although we're
unable to find that closed form solution
for the inverse cdf it's not too hard to
approximate it using numerical analysis
and i've left a link here that can
direct you to the right places for that
so now thankfully what we can do is we
can demonstrate this by using the point
percentile function that's actually
applied in scipy stats module so we can
use the point percentile function which
uses a numerical methodology to
approximate these values and essentially
here we're just going to sample from our
uniform distribution and use that as an
input to our point percentile function
our inverse
cdf approximation
we can see here that we get a very low
computation time of 0.068
and our kurtosis and skew is
essentially the same as a normally
distributed variable
now it's a really important to remember
though that while we have access to
numpy and python this is the best way to
do it for sure essentially they're using
one of these inverse
cdf approximation algorithms and the one
that they're using is cigarette
algorithm but it's important to know
that numpy has been directly implemented
in c and therefore this implementation
executes way quicker than anything that
we could implement so of course we would
use our random normal between zero and
one and then our number of samples that
we want to actually sample from so this
computation time is the lowest at point
zero three so now to the point of the
matter we've gone through how you can
generate all these pseudo-random numbers
that of course are seeded with a number
and that's what makes this sequence
non-random
turns out that pseudo-random numbers are
a bad choice for monte carlo simulation
so how are we going to demonstrate this
well let's consider pairs of independent
uniformly distributed random numbers and
we've got 500 points here and what
you'll observe is that you can see that
there are clumps
in this distribution
and then there are empty spaces so it's
important to remember that of course
both of these variables are independent
uniformly distributed so every point on
the graph is equally likely however we
do observe these clumpiness and these
empty spaces eventually if we sampled
enough points then the initial clumps
and empty spaces would be swamped and
then all the large number of points
would be spread evenly but unfortunately
with monte carlo simulation the whole
aim is to often reduce the number of
samples and decrease the computation
time as has been the whole point with
variance reduction techniques so pseudo
random numbers introduce bias through
clumpiness and through empty spaces
now in contrast quasi random numbers
offers a solution to this problem they
are often called low discrepancy
sequences and are designed to appear
random but not clumpy so they have the
same statistical properties as random
variables much like pseudorandom
variables however they do not have
clumpiness in their distributions
however they avoid trying to be clumpy
in the way that they're simulated so
quasi random samples are not independent
from the previous ones in other words it
remembers the previous samples and it
attempts to position itself away from
other samples so there are many methods
to produce quasi-random numbers that uh
provide several low discrepancy
sequences some of these sequences are
the full ray sequence the halton the
reverse halton sequence hassel grove
sequence and the sobel sequence the
behavior is ideal for obtaining fast
convergence in monte carlo simulation
and we're going to show
the halton and sobble methods because
these are implemented in scipy if you
wanted to use other methods then you
would have to find specific packages
like ot turn
that could actually be used to generate
these other sequences so take a look at
this link here
now from scipy stats we're going to
import qmc and this is for mo this is
specifically for monte carlo simulation
so firstly we're going to look at the
halton distribution and we've got our
sampler which is halton which is
defined on a certain dimensionality and
then we sample a specific number of
random variables i've also done this for
the halton normal distribution where we
take our halton
distribution so picture these as the
uniform distributions and then we go to
then use the point percentile function
from scipy stats norm
to actually generate our normally
distributed variables
so just taking our halton uniform
distribution with dimensions 2 as we
were before you can see that this plot
is a lot less clumpy and has less spaces
than previous
now we're going to look at the sobolf
function so with a subtle function we
can only generate samples of number
equals 2
to the power of m so it's base 2 numbers
so here we've got m which is 2 to the
power of m is the number of variables
we're going to be simulating and for the
normal distribution again i'm using the
point percentile function from psi pi
now if we look at how these are
distributed
in our dimension 2
with 9
with 2 to the power of 9 number of
variables so
512 then we can see we get a much more
even distribution with less empty spaces
than our pseudo-random numbers so what's
the significance of this well let's take
a look at a real monte carlo convergence
between the pseudo and quasi random
numbers so we're going to just consider
european option which we have an exact
solution for in terms of black shoals
and we're going to look at the different
methods of sampling to see if the rate
of convergence changes so our pseudo
sampling methods that we're going to
compare are the add 12 uniform variables
together and then subtract 6 our box
mueller methodology our polar rejection
method and then our inverse transform
sampling that's implemented by like the
likes of numpy so we're also going to
look at our quasi-sampling methods with
the which are the halton and the subtle
from scipy so
i'm just implementing the black shoals
formula here with the following
variables
interest rate of one percent underlying
of 30
strike of 32 a time of 240 days and a
volatility of 30 percent
now if we take a call option on that
basis then we get a black shoals price
of 2.1
so for our results i'm going to store
them in this dictionary called results
and i'm going to call functions of each
one of these
different
methods from this functions dictionary
we're going to test a whole
different array of numbers
to test the convergence
as we increase the numbers with
different sampling methods so we're just
running through the monte carlo
simulation and we're going to sample
different random variables with the
different methods
note that i have to do sobel
in a different way because again it's
using base 2 to calculate the number of
simulations so here in our graph i'm
showing the difference between all these
different methods over the number of
simulations that we're actually using
the number of random variables we're
generating and the relative pricing
error on the y-axis so the relative
pricing area is the price that we're
getting from our monte carlo simulation
minus our exact solution from the black
shoals so as you can see we've achieved
convergence in the black and the
purple line extremely quickly with our
halton and our subtle method so they are
quasi random numbers and that's because
we've got remember even distribution
which is very ideal for monte carlo
whereas the pseudo-random numbers take a
long time or a large number of simulated
variables to actually achieve the same
convergence on that price
so
take a look at this graph in your own
time and do your own analysis but
essentially we get large benefits from
using quasi random numbers within our
monte carlo simulation especially when
the goal is to reduce computation time
and increase efficiency thank you very
much for watching the video if you
enjoyed this i'd really appreciate if
you left like on this video and
subscribe to the channel for more
content like it if you're really keen on
seeing uh how i go about my process and
joining like mind members in the quant
community please consider joining my
patreon channel and link in the
description
see you later